<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Deprecated Excalibur Products</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Deprecated Excalibur Products">
            <p>
                Over time several Excalibur products have reached the
                end of their lifecycle. This page documents the deprecated
                components.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Excalibur-Compatibility">
                <p>
                    Compatibility was a library consisting of several utility classes that
                    Excalibur had ceased developing with the aim of focusing on the charter.
                </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th colspan="2">Replacements</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Package</th>
                        <th>Replacement</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>o.a.a.excalibur.cli</td>
                        <td><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/cli/">Commons-CLI</a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>o.a.a.excalibur.collections</td>
                        <td><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/collections/">Commons-Collections</a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>o.a.a.excalibur.concurrent</td>
                        <td>Doug Leas <a href="http://gee.cs.oswego.edu/dl/classes/EDU/oswego/cs/dl/util/concurrent/intro.html">Concurrent Library</a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>o.a.a.excalibur.io</td>
                        <td><a href="http://spice.codehaus.org/salt">Spice-Salt</a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>o.a.a.excalibur.naming</td>
                        <td><a href="http://spice.codehaus.org/jndikit">Spice-JNDIKit</a></td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Excalibur-Component">
                <p>
                    ECM (Excalibur Component Manager) was our first container. It's still in use in
                    quite a few projects, but has not been under active development for about two
                    years, as we've written a much better container that is (almost) completely
                    backwards compatible.
                </p>

                <blockquote><strong>Replacement:</strong> <a href="/fortress/index.html">Excalibur-Fortress</a></blockquote>

                <p>
                    Some old documentation about ECM is still available
                    <a href="component.html">here</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Excalibur-Configuration">
                <p>
                    Excalibur-Configuration was a utility library to manipulate configuration trees.
                    Configuration had never been released and the original developers have
                    redeveloped the code elsewhere. The following table lists the replacement
                    packages for Excalibur-Configuration.
                </p>

                <blockquote><strong>Replacement:</strong> <a href="http://spice.codehaus.org/configkit">Spice-Configkit</a></blockquote>

                <p>
                    Some old documentation about Excalibur-Configuration is still available
                    <a href="configuration.html">here</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Excalibur-Event">
                <p>
                    Excalibur-Event was an extensive component library to aid in concurrent
                    programming. This package has gradually evolved into a much better package
                    maintained elsewhere. The following table lists the replacement
                    packages for Excalibur-Event.
                </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th colspan="2">Replacements</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Package</th>
                        <th>Replacement</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>o.a.excalibur.event</td>
                        <td><a href="http://dist.d-haven.org/event/">D-Haven-Event</a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>o.a.excalibur.mpool</td>
                        <td><a href="http://dist.d-haven.org/managed-pool/">D-Haven-Managed-Pool</a></td>
                    </tr>
                </table>

                <p>
                    Some old documentation about Excalibur-Event is still available
                    <a href="event/index.html">here</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Excalibur-i18n">
                <p>
                    Excalibur-i18n was a very small utility library to aid in the use of localized
                    resources. This library stored these resources in an inconvenient location. A
                    much better package has been developed elsewhere.
                </p>

                <blockquote><strong>Replacement:</strong> <a href="http://spice.codehaus.org/salt">Spice-Salt</a></blockquote>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Excalibur-Testcase">
                <p>
                    Excalibur-Testcase was a library to aid unit testing of components. It provided
                    an extended TestCase class that would set up an ECM instance for you. Since we
                    now all know this is a bad idea (no component should be tested against an actual
                    container implementation, only in isolation), it has been deprecated along with
                    ECM, with no direct replacement.
                </p>
                <blockquote><strong>Replacement:</strong> <em>none</em></blockquote>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
