<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="hammant@apache.org">Paul Hammant</author>
    <author email="bloritsch@apache.org">Berin Loritsch</author>
    <title>Conclusion</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Conclusion">
  <p>
    Maybe you are already convinced, but need some help convincing
    your colleagues that Avalon is right for you.  Maybe you need
    some convincing yourself.  Either way, this chapter will help
    wrap everything up, and provide you with some convincing arguments.
    We all need to fight Fear, Uncertainty, and Doubt (FUD) with the
    Open Source model.  For arguments on the validity of Open Source,
    I will direct you to Eric S. Raymond's excellent treatises on the
    subject (
      <a href="http://www.tuxedo.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/">http://www.tuxedo.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/</a> ).
    Regardless of your opinions on his politics, the
    papers he wrote and compiled into the book <em>The Cathedral
    and the Bazaar</em> will give you the information you need to
    be convinced about the open source model as a whole.
  </p>
  </section>
  <section name="Avalon Works">
    <p>
      The bottom line is that Avalon accomplishes the goal it was
      originally designed to fulfill.  Avalon does not introduce new
      concepts and ideas, but rather uses and formalizes several concepts
      that have stood the test of time.  The newest concept that influenced
      the design of Avalon is the Separation of Concerns pattern introduced
      sometime around 1995.  Even then, Separation of Concerns is a
      formalization of System Analysis techniques.
    </p>
    <p>
      Avalon's user base is measured in the hundreds.  Several projects
      like Apache Cocoon, Apache JAMES, and Jesktop are all built on Avalon.
      Developers for those projects are users of Avalon Framework.  Because of
      the number of users Avalon has, it is very well tested.
    </p>
    <subsection name="Designed by the Best Minds">3
      <p>
        The authors of Avalon recognize that we are not the sole experts
        on server side programming.  We use concepts and ideas from other
        people's research.  We respond to feedback from our users.  Avalon
        is not just designed by the five developers mentioned in the
        introduction -- the people who came up with the concepts of Inversion
        of Control, Separation of Concerns, and Component Oriented
        Programming designed it.
      </p>
      <p>
        The beauty of Open Source projects is that the result is an
        amalgamation of the best ideas and the best code.  Avalon has gone
        through periods of testing ideas and rejecting them because there
        was a better solution.  You can take the knowledge gained by the
        Avalon team and use it in your own systems.  You can take the
        predefined components in Excalibur and use them in your own
        projects -- they have been tested to work under heavy load without
        errors.
      </p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Compatible License">
      <p>
        The <em>Apache Software License</em> (ASL) is compatible
        with just about every other license known.  The biggest known
        exceptions are the <em>GNU Public License</em> (GPL)
        and the <em>Lesser GNU Public License</em> (LGPL).  The
        important thing is that the ASL is friendly to corporate development,
        and does not force you to release your source code if you don't want
        to.  It is the same license used for the Apache Software Foundation's
        venerable HTTP server.
      </p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Pooled Research">
      <p>
        Most of Avalon's users contribute back to the project in some way.
        This spreads the cost of developing, debugging, and documenting the
        framework across several users.  It also means that Avalon's code
        has gone through a more extensive peer review than would ever be
        possible in one company.  In addition, users of Avalon support
        Avalon.  While it is true open source projects do not typically have
        a help desk or telephone support line, we do have a mailing list.
        Many times your questions can be answered in less time on the list
        than it would take on some support lines.
      </p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Simplified Analysis and Design">
      <p>
        Developing on Avalon helps the developer to get into a mindset.
        That mindset focuses the efforts on how to discover Components and
        Services.  Since many of the details regarding the life of the
        Components and Services in the system are already analyzed and
        designed, the developer only has to choose which ones they need.
      </p>
      <p>
        It is important to state that Avalon development does not replace
        traditional Object Oriented Analysis and Design, but enhances it.
        You are still using the same techniques you did before, only now
        you have a tool set you can use to achieve your design faster.
      </p>
    </subsection>
  </section>
  <section name="Avalon is Ready">
    <p>
      Avalon Framework, Avalon Excalibur, Avalon Phoenix and Avalon LogKit
      are ready for you to use now.  They are mature, powerful products and
      they are only getting better!
    </p>
  </section>
 </body>
</document>
