<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed  under the  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT  WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS  OF ANY KIND, either  express  or
implied.

See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="leif.AT.tanukisoftware.DOT.com">Leif Mortenson</author>
        <title>Excalibur Instrument - XML Client - Instrument</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="XML Client - Instrument">
            <p>
                The Instrument URL is used to obtain information about a particular
                Instrument, including any permanent or leased Samples.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Request">
            <p>
                Request parameters are set as HTTP GET parameters when sending the
                request to the server.
            </p>
            <p>
                For example, to request the <b>instrument-manager.memory</b> Instrument,
                the following URL can be used:
            </p>
            <source><a href="http://localhost:15080/instrument.xml?name=instrument-manager.memory">http://localhost:15080/instrument.xml?name=instrument-manager.memory</a></source>
            <subsection name="Parameters">
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Name</th>
                        <th>Data Type</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                        <th>Notes</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><b>name</b></td>
                        <td>String</td>
                        <td>
                            The fully qualified name of the Instrument being requested.
                        </td>
                        <td>Required.</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><b>packed</b></td>
                        <td>boolean</td>
                        <td>
                            Normally XML is returned in a human-readable pretty format
                            with indenting and line feeds.   While this makes it easy to
                            work with, it also adds several percent to the size of the
                            XML returned to the client.  By setting the packed parameter
                            to "true", all white space is removed from the generated XML. 
                        </td>
                        <td>Optional.  Defaults to "false".</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><b>recurse</b></td>
                        <td>boolean</td>
                        <td>
                            By default, the Instrument URL will return information
                            about the Instrument itself along with any direct
                            permanent or leased Samples.  By setting the recurse
                            parameter to "true", the generated XML will include the
                            full attribute list of the Samples.  This can be quite
                            useful to initialize a client application with the current
                            state of the Instrument tree.  Once initialized, it is more
                            efficient to monitor the <b>state-version</b> attributes
                            and only request information which has changed.
                        </td>
                        <td>Optional.  Defaults to "false".</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Response XML">
            <p>
                The XML received in the response will be UTF-8 encoded.  The root node
                will be named <b>instrument</b> and have the following attributes.
            </p>
            <p>
                Each Sample will be given a <b>sample</b> child element.
                If the <b>recurse</b> parameter was specified in the request
                then each of the Samples will have all of the attributes
                described for the
                <a href="xml-client-sample.html">Sample</a> URL.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Attributes">
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Name</th>
                        <th>Data Type</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><b>name</b></td>
                        <td>String</td>
                        <td>
                            Fully qualified name of the Instrument.  This
                            name is used to reference the Instrument in
                            other requests.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><b>description</b></td>
                        <td>String</td>
                        <td>
                            A human readable descripton of the Instrument.  It
                            is optionally specified in the
                            <a href="configuration.html">Instrument configuration file</a>
                            and can not be modified from a client.  If not configured
                            then the description will be equal to the last token in the
                            name.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><b>type</b></td>
                        <td>int</td>
                        <td>
                            Specifies the type of the Instrument.
                            <ul>
                                <li><b>1</b> - Counter Instrument</li>
                                <li><b>2</b> - Value Instrument</li>
                            </ul>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><b>state-version</b></td>
                        <td>int</td>
                        <td>
                            Current State-Version of the Instrument.  The
                            state version will be incremented whenever there are any
                            changes to the Instrument or any of its child
                            elements.  It can be compared with a last known state
                            version to decide whether or not it is necessary to to
                            request further details.
                            <p/>
                            If the application is running long enough, the
                            state version will eventially overflow.  To makes
                            sure your application will handle this case use
                            an equality test when comparing state versions.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><b>registered</b></td>
                        <td>boolean</td>
                        <td>
                            Indicates whether or not the Instrument has been registered
                            with the Instrument Manager after the application was started.
                            <p/>
                            It is possible for the Instrument to exist but not to have
                            been registered if the Instrument was declared in the
                            <a href="configuration.html">Instrument configuration file</a>
                            or had any outstanding leases that survived from a previous
                            application invocation.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><b>configured</b></td>
                        <td>boolean</td>
                        <td>
                            Indicates whether or not the Instrument has been declared
                            in the <a href="configuration.html">Instrument configuration file</a>.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Child Elements">
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Name</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><b>sample</b></td>
                        <td>
                            Sample elements will exist for each permanent or leased
                            Instrument Sample that is currently registered with this
                            Instrument.  Samples may be added or removed from this
                            list as the application runs so the <b>state-version</b>
                            of the parent <b>instrument</b> should be monitored for
                            changes.
                            <p/>
                            If the <b>recurse</b> parameter was set to "true" in the
                            request, an expanded list of attributes will be available.
                            See the documentation for the
                            <a href="xml-client-sample.html">Sample</a> URL for further
                            details.
                            <p/>
                            Attributes:
                            <table>
                                <tr>
                                    <th>Name</th>
                                    <th>Data Type</th>
                                    <th>Description</th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td><b>name</b></td>
                                    <td>String</td>
                                    <td>
                                        Fully qualified name of the Sample.  This
                                        name is used to reference the Sample in
                                        other requests.
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td><b>state-version</b></td>
                                    <td>int</td>
                                    <td>
                                        Current State-Version of the Sample.  The
                                        state version will be incremented whenever there
                                        are any changes to the Sample.  It can be compared
                                        with a last known state version to decide whether
                                        or not it is necessary to to request further
                                        details.
                                        <p/>
                                        If the application is running long enough, the
                                        state version will eventially overflow.  To make
                                        sure your application will handle this case use
                                        an equality test when comparing state versions.
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                            </table>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>