<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
     Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
     contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
     this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
     The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
     (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
     the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

     Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
     distributed  under the  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
     WITHOUT  WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS  OF ANY KIND, either  express  or
     implied.

     See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
     limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="leif.AT.tanukisoftware.DOT.com">Leif Mortenson</author>
        <title>Excalibur Instrument - XML Client Interface</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="XML Client">
            <p>
                The HTTP Connector makes it possible for remote applications to connect
                to an Instrument Manager.  The connector is capable of serving both
                HTML and XML formatted content which makes it possible to monitor
                and manipulate the Instruments registered with the Instrument Manager.
            </p>
            <p>
                Used correctly, this interface provides a powerful and efficient way to
                work with the Instrument Manager.
                The Swing based <a href="java-client.html">Java client</a> makes use of
                the XML interface to communicate with the Instrument Manager.
            </p>
            <p>
                The XML interface is enabled by default, but it is possible to disable it
                in the <a href="configuration.html">configuration</a> for the HTTP
                Connector.  It is also possible to set the HTTP Connector into a read-only
                mode, in which case several of the URLs listed below will be unavailable.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Interface URLs">
                <p>
                    Requests are made to the XML Client Interface using one or more of
                    the following URLs.  Any client which is capable of making HTTP
                    requests can be used.
                </p>
                <p>
                    All requests must be made using the HTTP GET method.  Currently POST
                    is not supported.  URL request parameters specific to each URL are
                    described in detail on each URL page below.
                </p>
                <p>
                    All requests and responsed are encoded using the UTF-8 encoding.
                    When building the URLs, it is very important that any text parameter
                    values be propperly URL Encoded.   English text will usually work but
                    if a future user begins using your application with another languange,
                    like Japanese, unencoded text will likely be corrupted when sending
                    the requests to the server.
                </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Name</th>
                        <th>URL</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-instrument-manager.html">Instrument Manager</a></td>
                        <td>/instrument-manager.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Instrument Manager URL is used to obtain information about the
                            Instrument Manager as a whole, including any root Instrumentables.
                            By providing a recurse parameter, it is possible to request the
                            entire instrument tree for the system in a single request.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-instrumentable.html">Instrumentable</a></td>
                        <td>/instrumentable.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Instrumentable URL is used to obtain information about a particular
                            Instrumentable, including any child Instrumentables or Instruments.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-instrument.html">Instrument</a></td>
                        <td>/instrument.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Instrument URL is used to obtain information about a particular
                            Instrument, including any permanent or leased Samples.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-sample.html">Sample</a></td>
                        <td>/sample.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Sample URL is used to obtain information about a particular
                            Sample.  To obtain the actual data points of the sample, the
                            <a href="xml-client-snapshot.html">Sample Snapshot</a> URL must
                            be used.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-snapshot.html">Sample Snapshot</a></td>
                        <td>/snapshot.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Sample Snapshot URL is used to request a snapshot of the contents
                            of a particular Sample.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-snapshots.html">Sample Snapshots</a></td>
                        <td>/snapshots.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Sample Snapshots URL work similar to the Sample Snapshot URL
                            except that it makes it possible to request snapshots for several
                            Samples in a single request.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-create-sample.html">Create Sample</a></td>
                        <td>/create-sample.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Create Sample URL is used to register a new Sample lease with the
                            Instrument Manager.   It is also possible to renew leases using this
                            URL.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-create-samples.html">Create Samples</a></td>
                        <td>/create-samples.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Create Samples URL is used to register multiple new Sample leases
                            with the Instrument Manager.   It is also possible to renew leases
                            using this URL.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-sample-lease.html">Sample Lease</a></td>
                        <td>/sample-lease.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Sample Lease URL is used to renew a lease on an existing
                            Sample.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-sample-leases.html">Sample Leases</a></td>
                        <td>/sample-leases.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Sample Lease URL is used to renew the leases on multiple
                            existing Samples.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><a href="xml-client-gc.html">Invoke Garbage Collection</a></td>
                        <td>/gc.xml</td>
                        <td>
                            The Invoke Garbage Collection URL is used to force the server
                            to immediately perform a Garbage Collection sweep of its memory.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>