<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
     Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
     contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
     this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
     The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
     (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
     the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
     
     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
     
     Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
     distributed  under the  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
     WITHOUT  WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS  OF ANY KIND, either  express  or
     implied.
     
     See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
     limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Event - Util</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Why Util Was Created">
            <p>
        Util was created to enable us to find out how many processors are
        on a system programmatically.  Unfortunately Sun does not think
        it is important to know these details through Java.  The Thread
        Manager uses this to automatically determine how many background
        threads it wants in the backing ThreadPool.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="When To Use Util">
            <p>
        Usually you won't use this package directly, unless you want to
        know how many processors a system has.  You might need to add a
        new CPU Parser that will find out the necessary information from
        environment variables or the /proc/ filesystem for a platform
        that is not currently supported.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Core Concepts">
            <p>
        Util has a SystemUtil which will load the correct CPU Parser for your
        platform.  If there is no maching CPU Parser will assume that there is
        only one processor for your system.
            </p>
            <section name="System Util">
                <p>
          The System Util will allow you to gather any platform specific
          information.  Some of the methods are simpler ways of accessing
          the System properties, and others are derived from the CPU Parser.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section name="CPU Parser">
                <p>
          The CPU Parser will allow you to gather essential information from
          your platform.  Unfortunately we cannot assume there is only one
          way to gather information for each platform.  If your platform is
          not supported directly, please send an email to the
                    <a href="mailto:users@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Users</a>
          mailing list with the new CPU Parser attached.  We should be able
          to include it in the next release.  We currently support the entire
          Microsoft Windows suite that supports Java, and Linux.  Since we
          don't currently have access to other machines, we can't support them
          yet.
                </p>
            </section>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
