<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
     Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation
     Licensed  under the  Apache License,  Version 2.0  (the "License");
     you may not use  this file  except in  compliance with the License.
     You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

     Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
     distributed  under the  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
     WITHOUT  WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS  OF ANY KIND, either  express  or
     implied.

     See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
     limitations under the License.
-->
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Fortress - Getting Started</title>

    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Getting Started">
            <p>
                This is a brief guide to getting you up and running with fortress.
                For complex topics like how to decompose a system into individual
                components, Seperation of Concerns, etc, refer to other documentation.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Getting your stuff together">
                <ul>
                    <li>If you haven't already, download and install the latest version
                of
                        <link href="http://ant.apache.org/">Apache Ant</link>.
                    </li>
                    <li>Get and install a CVS client (see
                        <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/cvsindex.html">here</link>
                for information on CVS).
                    </li>
                    <li>Check out the modules avalon, avalon-excalibur,
                avalon-logkit and jakarta-site</li>
                    <li>Use ant to build the various projects: avalon, logkit, excalibur fortress.
                If something goes wrong, run ant in verbose mode using the -v option and
                send the output to the avalon-user mailing list. Someone'll help you out.
                    </li>
                </ul>

                <p>Or, if you hate CVS, get a nightly build.</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Hello, world!">
                <p>You just built fortress, its dependencies, and its examples from cvs in
            the previous step. This enables you to (finally!) run a HelloWorld demo.
            change into the bin directory for the examples and run the
            scripts there (runswing.sh is a nice one).</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Well, duh! So now what?">
                <p>
                    <b>Play with the examples</b>
                </p>
                <p>After looking at the sources to the examples provided and figuring out
                what goes on (if you're an IDE person, run the examples in your IDE
                debugger! If you develop servlets, be sure to try to get the servlet
                example to run), the real cool but also the hard part begins.</p>

            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Converting from ECM">
                <p>If you're looking at converting an existing avalonized application that
                uses ECM, well, we want to write a tool that does this all but automatically
                for you. Not there yet though.</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Convert a non-avalon application">
                <p>The first thing you want to do is to create a fortress instance inside
                your applications main loop or bootstrap class. The second thing you want
                to do is identify the building blocks of your application, and transform
                them into avalon components (by making them passive, and extending the
                avalon framework lifecycle interfaces).
                Then, create the fortress configuration files to tell it about those new
                components, and transfer control over those components from your bootstrap
                code to fortress. Done!</p>
                <p>Okay, so it may not be so simple as it sounds, but that is the general
                idea. Just get started, and come and talk to us on the mailing list when
                you get lost.</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Creating a new application">
                <p>Start with the example that fits your enviroment (console, GUI
                or embedded), and simply start hacking from there. You'll want to think
                about the various tasks your app serves, and how to decompose your app
                into components that fit those tasks. The
                    <link href="http://avalon.apache.org/developing">Developing with Avalon</link>
                paper talks you through this.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Mastering Fortress">
                <p>
                The best way to learn about avalon and its concepts is to build your own
                container. Try and plug in your own implementations of the different parts
                of fortress, like a different ComponentHandler. Once you get a hang of it,
                come and join the avalon folks in their quest for the holy grail of
                software architecture!
                </p>
            </subsection>

        </section>
    </body>
</document>
