<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
     Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation
     Licensed  under the  Apache License,  Version 2.0  (the "License");
     you may not use  this file  except in  compliance with the License.
     You may obtain a copy of the License at
     
     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
     
     Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
     distributed  under the  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
     WITHOUT  WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS  OF ANY KIND, either  express  or
     implied.
     
     See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
     limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Event - MPool (Managed Pool)</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Why MPool Was Created">
            <p>
        MPool (Managed Pool) was created as an experiment in dynamic
        pool management.  The theory is that by determining whether to
        shrink or grow a pool can be a costly endeavor.  That is
        especially true when you want to play with "intelligent" pools.
            </p>
            <p>
        What we observed after we used MPool in practice is that under
        load, pool sizing algorithms begin to choke the efficiency of
        the pool.  In fact, it can get so bad that it would be better
        not to have a pool at all.  An unbounded pool (one that does
        not shrink) is a resource hog, especially during inactive times.
        By moving the pool sizing logic into an asyncronous Command,
        we were able to achieve the efficiency of an unbounded pool
        while keeping an eye on pool size.  During times of inactivity
        we destroy pooled objects that we don't need.  During times of
        stress, we create a new object immediately and in a background
        process we add new objects.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="When To Use MPool">
            <p>
        Use MPool any time you need a pool without hard limits, and you
        expect heavy loads.  The pool size is checked periodically, so
        we don't incur extra overhead of having to check that while the
        pool size grows and shrinks.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Core Concepts">
            <p>
        MPool has two pool types: fixed size and variable size.  A fixed
        size pool is not managed externally.  There is a fixed limit to
        the number of resources it can manage so we don't have to manage
        it.  A variable sized pool is a managed pool.  A managed pool will
        be created by the PoolManager, and that manager will manage all
        of its pool sizes in the background.
            </p>
            <section name="Object Factory">
                <p>
          An Object Factory is what the pools use to create new objects
          or destroy old ones.  They are particularly helpful when there
          is a complex creation/destruction policy.  They are also essential
          for ManageablePools.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section name="Pool">
                <p>
          The base Pool interface is how the client code interacts with
          the pool.  You acquire and release pooled objects from the
          pool.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section name="Managable Pool">
                <p>
          A Managable Pool is a special interface that allows a PoolManager
          to register itself with a "magic key" so that the managed pool
          only responds to the PoolManager responsible for it.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section name="Pool Manager">
                <p>
          The Pool Manager is how you obtain a Managable Pool.  It also
          takes care of the management functions for that pool.
                </p>
            </section>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
